Papers of the President's Mediation Commission on Microfilm 5751 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Papers of the President's Mediation Commission on Microfilm
1917-1919
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
President's Mediation Commission
5751 mf
0.33 cubic feet
3 microfilm reels
Microfilm, records (documents).
Included are all of the Commission's records housed in the National Archives; these are, however, incomplete and officially described as fragmentary. This collection consists mainly of testimony of witnesses before the Commission in hearings held in Globe, Clifton, and Bisbee, Arizona and in Salt Lake City, Utah. Also included are reports, correspondence, and other general materials of the Commission.
3337351
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 26, 2012
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 02, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The President's Mediation Commission represented a partial federal response to two vital aspects of wartime labor policy: 1) the spreading wave of strikes which interfered with the production of goods deemed vital to the war effort, and 2) the growth of labor radicalism associated with the Industrial Workers of the World (IWW), which precipitated widespread state and local repression of labor's rights and murderous vigilantism. Samuel Gompers, the president of the AFL, feared both the growth of the IWW and the ensuing vigilantism, which threatened AFL unions. Gompers desired a federal policy that would simultaneously curb the IWW and protect "legitimate" trade unions. As vigilantism against labor spread throughout the American West in July-August 1917, Gompers used his influence in Washington to urge the appointment of a special presidential commission to investigate labor-capital relations. In August, William B. Wilson, the secretary of labor, began to urge the same policy on President Wilson. The secretary desired a commission that would effectively mediate the substantive issues causing labor discontent and would also eliminate the IWW. To cloak his proposed commission's true purposes, which included the destruction of the IWW, W.B. Wilson suggestd that it investigate labor disputes unrelated to IWW strikes. On August 31, he recommended to the president a five-person commission to consist of the following members: J.L. Spangler, a Pennsylvania Dutch coal mine operator with a reputation for dealing fairly with the United Mine Workers (UMW); Verner Z. Reed, a Colorado enrepreneur and liberal Roman Catholic; John H. Wlaker, a former UMW official and then president of the Illinois State Federation of Labor; E.P. Marsh, a conservative AFL unionist and president of the Washington State Federation of Labor; and William B. Wilson as the chair. More important than any of the five suggested commission members was the person Wilson selected as his secretary, Felix Frankfurter.
Officially appointed by President Wilson on September 19, 1917, the President's Mediation Commission operated on the basis of guidelines set by Frankfurter. Those guidelines recommended the promotion of AFL-style trade unionism, the elimination of subversvie IWW locals, and the encouragement of industrial democracy. The Commission began its formal investigations and hearings in the Arizona copper mining districts on October 6, 1917. Its members later traveled to the Butte, Montana, copper district; the forest district of the Pacific Northwest; San Francisco, where they investigated a dispute affecting telephone operators; and Chicago, where they studied labor discontentment in the packinghouses. In January, 1918, the Commission presented its findings and recommendations to the president, which largely followed the original Frankfurter guidelines and which were subsequently published as a special bulletin by the Department of Labor.
Scope and Contents
Included are all of the Commission's records housed in the National Archives; these are, however, incomplete and officially described as fragmentary. This collection consists mainly of testimony of witnesses before the Commission in hearings held in Globe, Clifton, and Bisbee, Arizona and in Salt Lake City, Utah. Also included are reports, correspondence, and other general materials of the Commission.
Witnesses include representatives of various trades as well as local businessmen, mine operators, and citizens' groups, notably the Loyalty League and the Citizens' Protective League. The testimony includes discussions of labor relations and strikes, primarily involving western mining companies, the Bisbee, Arizona deportation of IWW members, longshoremen, lumbering, farm labor, and railroads, as well as legislation and union relations with law enforcement agencies.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Arrangement
Series Sessions at Globe, Arizona, 1914
Sub-Series Introduction, 1915 Sub-Series Witnesses Appearing before the Commission on behalf of Striking Miners, 1917 Sub-Series Witnesses Appearing before the Commission on behalf of Men Working during the Strike, 1917 Sub-Series Witnesses Appearing before the Commission on behalf of Different Crafts' Union, 1917 Sub-Series Mine Managers' Presentation, 1917 Sub-Series Committee Representing Businessmen of Globe, Arizona, 1917 Sub-Series Committee Representing Businessmen of Globe, not Members of the Loyalty League, 1917
Series Sessions at Clifton, Arizona, 1917
Sub-Series Introduction, 1917 Sub-Series Miners' Representatives, 1917 Sub-Series Mine Managers and Representatives, 1917 Sub-Series Shift Bosses, 1917 Sub-Series Citizens, 1917 Sub-Series Railroad Employees, 1917
Series Sessions at Bisbee, Arizona, 1917
Sub-Series Introduction, 1917 Sub-Series Witnesses Appearing before the Commission, 1917 Sub-Series Committee from Warren District Commercial Club and Citizens Protective League, 1917
Series Sessions at Bisbee, Arizona (continued), 1917
Sub-Series Witness Appearing before the Commission, 1917 Sub-Series Mine Managers' Statements, 1917 Sub-Series Employees' Committee of Copper Queen Consolidated Mining Company, 1917 Sub-Series Witness Appearing before the Commission, 1917 Sub-Series Mine Managers' Statements, 1917
Series Sessions at Salt Lake City, Utah, 1918
Sub-Series Introduction, 1918 Sub-Series State Industrial Commission of Utah Testimony, 1918 Sub-Series Testimony of Labor Representatives, 1918 Sub-Series Correspondence and General Materials, 1917-1918
Anarchism, United States.; Anarchists, United States.; Deportation, United States.; Governmental investigations, United States.; Labor policy, United States.; Subversive activities, United States.; Labor disputes -- Nonferrous metal industries -- United States; Labor violence -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Copper industry -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Nonferrous metal industries -- Arizona; Strikes and lockouts -- Nonferrous metal industries -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Nonferrous metal industries -- Utah; Copper miners -- Labor unions -- Arizona; Copper miners -- Labor unions -- Utah; Miners -- Labor unions -- United States; Boehm, Randolph.; Dubofsky, Melvyn, 1934-; Industrial Workers of the World; United States. President's Mediation Commission
3337351
- Series Sessions at Globe, Arizona, 1914
  Scope and Contents
  October 9-16, 1917
  - Sub-Series Introduction, 1915
    - Title Page, 1916; 1 (Reel 1)
      1p.
    - Table of Contents, 1917; 2 (Reel 1)
      3pp.
  - Sub-Series Witnesses Appearing before the Commission on behalf of Striking Miners, 1917
    - J. F. Smith, Miner, 1917; 3 (Reel 1)
      2pp.
    - Joseph D. Cannon, Organizer, International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers (IUMM and SW)., 1917; 4 (Reel 1)
      119pp.
    - Charles H. Moyer, President, IUMM and SW., 1917; 5 (Reel 1)
      57pp.
  - Sub-Series Witnesses Appearing before the Commission on behalf of Men Working during the Strike, 1917
    - W. B. Nash, Chairman, Board of Supervisors, 1917; 6 (Reel 1)
      5pp.
    - Victor M. Kelly, Miner, 1917; 7 (Reel 1)
      65pp.
    - S. J. Harlan, Miner, 1917; 8 (Reel 1)
    - D. D. Woodruff, Miner, 1917; 9 (Reel 1)
      4pp.
    - H. A. Clark, Miner., 1917; 10 (Reel 1)
      21pp.
    - A. C. Belcher, Miner, 1917; 11 (Reel 1)
      10pp.
  - Sub-Series Witnesses Appearing before the Commission on behalf of Different Crafts' Union, 1917
    - E. D. Harrington, Chairman of the Committee of Allied Crafts., 1917; 12 (Reel 1)
      32pp.
    - Speech of Joseph D. Cannon, Union Organizer, before Citizens of Globe-Miami District, Speaking on Labor Conditions., 1917; 13 (Reel 1)
      19pp.
    - M. Kennedy, Miner., 1917; 14 (Reel 1)
      14pp.
    - H. S. Blackman, Miner, 1917; 15 (Reel 1)
      42pp.
    - D. D. Woodruff, Miner, Recalled, 1917; 16 (Reel 1)
      28pp.
    - George Graham, Miner, 1917; 17 (Reel 1)
    - P. G. Lloyd, Miner, 1917; 18 (Reel 1)
    - Alex Graydon, Miner, 1917; 19 (Reel 1)
      9pp.
    - William Penrose, Miner, 1917; 20 (Reel 1)
    - W. A. King, Miner, 1917; 21 (Reel 1)
      6pp.
    - John Harper, Deputy District Mining Inspector., 1917; 22 (Reel 1)
      36pp.
    - E. D. Harrington, Chairman of the Committee of Allied Crafts, Recalled., 1917; 23 (Reel 1)
    - George H. Williams, Mine Engineer., 1917; 24 (Reel 1)
      13pp.
    - J. Tom Lewis, Fireman., 1917; 25 (Reel 1)
      54pp.
    - A. E. Denton, Motorman., 1917; 26 (Reel 1)
      22pp.
    - F. L. Perry, President, Electrical Workers' Union., 1917; 27 (Reel 1)
    - P. C. Renaud, Miner, 1917; 28 (Reel 1)
    - Martin Busnek, Miner, 1917; 29 (Reel 1)
      8pp.
    - Jim Bowie, Miner, 1917; 30 (Reel 1)
    - Walter Self, Miner, 1917; 31 (Reel 1)
    - A. C. Leach, Carpenter, 1917; 32 (Reel 1)
    - Fred Montgomery, Foreman, 1917; 33 (Reel 1)
    - Mr. Peraty, Boilermaker, 1917; 34 (Reel 1)
    - Thomas Russer, Smelter man., 1917; 35 (Reel 1)
  - Sub-Series Mine Managers' Presentation, 1917
    - Statement by Secretary of Labor, W. B. Wilson, 1917; 36 (Reel 1)
    - Discussion between Managers and Commissioners, 1917; 37 (Reel 1)
      41pp.
  - Sub-Series Committee Representing Businessmen of Globe, Arizona, 1917
    - Statement by Secretary of Labor, W. B. Wilson, 1917; 38 (Reel 1)
    - Mr. McKillop, Lawyer, 1917; 39 (Reel 1)
    - Mr. Geare, Businessman., 1917; 40 (Reel 1)
      20pp.
    - Discussion between Members of Committee and Commissioners., 1917; 41 (Reel 1)
    - George R. Hill, President, Loyalty League., 1917; 42 (Reel 1)
      39pp.
  - Sub-Series Committee Representing Businessmen of Globe, not Members of the Loyalty League, 1917
    - Harry Gordy, Store Owner, 1917; 43 (Reel 1)
    - William Bendall, Grocer, 1917; 44 (Reel 1)
    - H. R. Turner, Barber., 1917; 45 (Reel 1)
    - L. T. Gaine, Theatre Operator, 1917; 46 (Reel 1)
    - G. A. Harbin, Secretary: Cooks and Waiters' Union., 1917; 47 (Reel 1)
    - Stenographic Reporters' Certificate, 1917; 48 (Reel 1)
- Series Sessions at Clifton, Arizona, 1917
  October 25-30, 1917
  - Sub-Series Introduction, 1917
    - Title Page, 1917; 1 (Reel 2)
    - Table of Contents, 1917; 2 (Reel 2)
    - Statement by Secretary of Labor, W. B. Wilson., 1917; 3 (Reel 2)
  - Sub-Series Miners' Representatives, 1917
    - H. S. McClusky, Union Member, IUMM and SW., 1917; 4 (Reel 2)
      26pp.
    - J. A. Wellington, Miner., 1917; 5 (Reel 2)
      37pp.
    - S. A. Heath, Carpenter, 1917; 6 (Reel 2)
    - C. R. Clifford, Machinist, 1917; 7 (Reel 2)
    - P. M. Vargas, Boilermaker., 1917; 8 (Reel 2)
      100pp.
    - John Murray, Secretary, Pan-American Federation of Labor Conference Committee., 1917; 9 (Reel 2)
      18pp.
    - C. J. Brooke, Store Department, Arizona Copper Company., 1917; 10 (Reel 2)
    - Charles H. Moyer, President, IUMM and SW., 1917; 11 (Reel 2)
      7pp.
  - Sub-Series Mine Managers and Representatives, 1917
    - Norman Carmichael, Arizona Copper Company., 1917; 12 (Reel 2)
      94pp.
    - J. W. Bennie, Shannon Copper Company., 1917; 13 (Reel 2)
    - Milton McLean, Phelps Dodge Corporation., 1917; 14 (Reel 2)
    - E. W. Lewis, judge., 1917; 15 (Reel 2)
    - P. B. [P. G. ] Scotland, Arizona, Copper Company., 1917; 16 (Reel 2)
      33pp.
    - John Christy, Mine Owner., 1917; 17 (Reel 2)
      12pp.
  - Sub-Series Shift Bosses, 1917
    - H. P. Hill, Foreman, Humboldt Mine, Arizona Copper Company, 1917; 18 (Reel 2)
    - George Miller, Machine Foreman, Arizona Copper Company, 1917; 19 (Reel 2)
    - Lee Lawhead, Standard Property, Phelps Dodge Corporation., 1917; 20 (Reel 2)
  - Sub-Series Citizens, 1917
    - J. Y. Ainsa, Mexican-American., 1917; 21 (Reel 2)
      24pp.
    - W. B. Kelly, Businessman., 1917; 22 (Reel 2)
      15pp.
    - J. F. Gaines, Craftsman, 1917; 23 (Reel 2)
    - J. F. Nichols, Mine Operator., 1917; 24 (Reel 2)
      11pp.
  - Sub-Series Railroad Employees, 1917
    - Ross Thomas, Enginemen's Representative, Arizona and New Mexico Railroad Company and the Coronado Railway, 1917; 25 (Reel 2)
    - W. H. Moses, Enginemen's Representative, Arizona and New Mexico Railroad Company and the Coronado Railway, 1917; 26 (Reel 2)
    - J. M. Cline, Enginemen's Representative, Arizona and New Mexico Railroad Company and the Coronado Railway Company, 1917; 27 (Reel 2)
    - Stenographic Reporter's Certificate, 1917; 28 (Reel 2)
- Series Sessions at Bisbee, Arizona, 1917
  November 1-5, 1917
  - Sub-Series Introduction, 1917
    - Title Page, 1917; 29 (Reel 2)
    - Table of Contents, 1917; 30 (Reel 2)
  - Sub-Series Witnesses Appearing before the Commission, 1917
    - George E. Kellogg, Manager of Telephone Company., 1917; 31 (Reel 2)
    - J. F. McDonald, Deputy U. S. Marshal, 1917; 32 (Reel 2)
    - Fred N. Brown, Union Organizer., 1917; 33 (Reel 2)
    - Frank J. Vaughn, President, Painters' Union, 1917; 34 (Reel 2)
    - Edward Massey, Deputy State Mine Inspector., 1917; 35 (Reel 2)
    - Frank A. Thomas, Police Court Judge., 1917; 36 (Reel 2)
    - Thomas N. English, Deportee, 1917; 37 (Reel 2)
    - E. P. McCoy, President, Local Trades Assembly., 1917; 38 (Reel 2)
    - Charles Ward, Industrial Workers of the World (IWW), Deportee, 1917; 39 (Reel 2)
    - John Glen Wilson, Carpenter-Contractor, 1917; 40 (Reel 2)
    - Mrs. Rosa McKay, Legislator., 1917; 41 (Reel 2)
    - Harry Wheeler, Sheriff, Cochise County., 1917; 42 (Reel 2)
      50pp.
    - M. W. Merrill, Miner, Member of the Loyalty League., 1917; 43 (Reel 2)
      43pp.
    - Basset T. Watkins, Deputy Sheriff and Shift Boss., 1917; 44 (Reel 2)
  - Sub-Series Committee from Warren District Commercial Club and Citizens Protective League, 1917
    - J. C. Ryan, County Engineer and Deputy State Engineer, Chairman of Committee., 1917; 45 (Reel 2)
      96pp. Includes Statistical Data, Relief Activities, and Correspondence.
- Series Sessions at Bisbee, Arizona (continued), 1917
  - Sub-Series Witness Appearing before the Commission, 1917
    - Walter E. Hawthorne, Photographer, Non-Union Deportee, 1917; 1 (Reel 3)
  - Sub-Series Mine Managers' Statements, 1917
    - G. H. Dowell, Copper Queen Branch Manager, Phelps Dodge Corporation, 1917; 2 (Reel 3)
    - Notarized Depositions on Union Intimidation, 1917; 3 (Reel 3)
    - Statement of Action, Local 106, IUMM and SW, 1917; 4 (Reel 3)
    - Union Press Releases, July 11, 1917, IUMM and SW, 5 (Reel 3)
    - G. H. Dowell, Copper Queen Branch Manager, Phelps Dodge Corporation, 1917; 6 (Reel 3)
    - E. E. Ellinwood, Judge, Bisbee, Arizona, 1917; 7 (Reel 3)
    - W. B. Gohring, Calumet and Arizona Mining Company, 1917; 8 (Reel 3)
      25pp.
    - Arthur S. Houle, Shattuck-Arizona Copper Company, 1917; 9 (Reel 3)
    - Ernest W. Lewis, Judge, Phoenix, Arizona, 1917; 10 (Reel 3)
  - Sub-Series Employees' Committee of Copper Queen Consolidated Mining Company, 1917
    - J. J. Harrington, Chairman of the Committee, 1917; 11 (Reel 3)
    - I. H. Strickland, Member of Committee, 1917; 12 (Reel 3)
    - C. F. Wagner, Member of Committee, 1917; 13 (Reel 3)
    - Roger Kennedy, Member of Committee, 1917; 14 (Reel 3)
    - Heber Taylor, Member of Committee, 1917; 15 (Reel 3)
    - Oscar Wynn, Member of Committee, 1917; 16 (Reel 3)
  - Sub-Series Witness Appearing before the Commission, 1917
    - Antonio Rodriguez, Deportee, 1917; 17 (Reel 3)
  - Sub-Series Mine Managers' Statements, 1917
    - G. H. Dowell, Copper Queen Branch Manager, Phelps Dodge Corporation, 1917; 18 (Reel 3)
      16pp.
    - W. B. Gohring, Calumet and Arizona Mining Company, 1917; 19 (Reel 3)
    - Harry Wheeler, Sheriff, Cochise County, 1917; 20 (Reel 3)
    - Stenographic Reporters' Certificate, 1917; 21 (Reel 3)
- Series Sessions at Salt Lake City, Utah, 1918
  July 24, 1918.
  - Sub-Series Introduction, 1918
    - Title Page, 1918; 22 (Reel 3)
    - Table of Contents, 1918; 23 (Reel 3)
  - Sub-Series State Industrial Commission of Utah Testimony, 1918
    - Commissioner Knerr: Utah Copper Company, 1918; 24 (Reel 3)
    - Commissioner Thatcher: Garfield Smelting Company, 1918; 25 (Reel 3)
    - Commissioner Knerr: Garfield Smelting Company, 1918; 26 (Reel 3)
    - Commissioner Knerr: Utah-Idaho Central Railway Company, 1918; 27 (Reel 3)
    - Commissioner Knerr: Ogden Packing and Provision Company, 1918; 28 (Reel 3)
  - Sub-Series Testimony of Labor Representatives, 1918
    - O. R. Henney, Labor Spokesman, Garfield Smelting Company, 1918; 29 (Reel 3)
    - R. M. Spalding, Mill Employees' Spokesman, Utah Copper Company, 1918; 30 (Reel 3)
      34pp.
    - W. N. Piggott, Secretary, Ogden Trades and Labor Assembly, Ogden Packing and Provision Company, 1918; 31 (Reel 3)
    - Joseph Lee, Machinists' Union and F. S. Dunn, Boilermakers' Union, Labor Spokesmen, Utah Copper Company and Garfield Mill and Smelter, 1918; 32 (Reel 3)
    - C. E. Woods and G. F. Lowery, Labor Spokesmen, Utah-Idaho Central Railway Company, 1918; 33 (Reel 3)
    - Mr. Lewis, President and Mr. Lamont, Secretary, Utah Branch, American Federation of Labor, 1918; 34 (Reel 3)
    - Ogden Packing and Provision Company--Discharged Employees, 1918; 35 (Reel 3)
    - Charles Jay, 1918; 36 (Reel 3)
    - George Penrod, 1918; 37 (Reel 3)
    - Eva Thompson, 1918; 38 (Reel 3)
    - John Boyce, 1918; 39 (Reel 3)
    - Con D. Silva, Union President, 1918; 40 (Reel 3)
    - Derk Koldewyn, 1918; 41 (Reel 3)
    - George Ransom, 1918; 42 (Reel 3)
  - Sub-Series Correspondence and General Materials, 1917-1918
    - Basis of Settlement of the Clifton-Morenci-Metcalf Strike, 1917; 43 (Reel 3)
      October 31, 1917. 7pp.
    - Regulations Promulgated for the War Industry of Woods and Mills of the Northwest, 1918; 44 (Reel 3)
      March 1, 1918. 2pp.
    - Exhibit of False Arrests for IWW Membership, 1917; 45 (Reel 3)
    - Proposed Legislation and Correspondence relating to the Creation of the President's Mediation Commission, 1917; 46 (Reel 3)
      April-May 1917. 41pp.
    - "Labor in the Inland Empire Lumber Territory. " Memo by Willard E. Hotchkiss, 1917; 47 (Reel 3)
      December 1917. 7pp.
    - Prepared Testimony of Lumbermen's Protective League, 1917; 48 (Reel 3)
      71pp.
    - General Correspondence of the President's Mediation Commission, 1918; 49 (Reel 3)
    - Decision of Shipbuilding Labor Adjustment Board Touching Disputes in San Francisco, Columbia River, and Puget Sound Districts, 1918; 50 (Reel 3)
    - Memo relating to Settlement of Longshoremen's Dispute at Puget Sound, 1918; 51 (Reel 3)
    - Memo on behalf of Employers of Waterfront Labor in the Ports of Puget Sound, 1918; 52 (Reel 3)
    - "Farm Labor and the IWW," Memo by Thorstein Veblen, 1918; 53 (Reel 3)
    - Exhibit A, Statement of Grievances by Agricultural Workers Industrial Union, 1918; 54 (Reel 3)
      April 8, 1918. 2pp.
    - Exhibit B. Affidavits of Maltreatment of Suspected IWW Members, 1917-1918; 55 (Reel 3)
    - Exhibit C, Statements of U. S. Forest Service Supervisors Expressing Satisfaction with IWW Labor Performance in Montana and Idaho Fire Control Programs, 1917- 1918; 56 (Reel 3)
    - Report of President's Mediation Commission on the Bisbee, Arizona, Deportations, 1917; 57 (Reel 3)
      November 6, 1917. 5pp.
    - Report of President's Mediation Commission, 1918; 58 (Reel 3)
      January 9, 1918. 11pp.
    - Telegrams on the Activities of the President's Mediation Commission, 1917; 59 (Reel 3)
      October-December 1917. 59pp.
    - Memo regarding Western IWW Situation, 1918; 60 (Reel 3)
      January 10, 1918. 6pp.
    - General Situation in the Northwest, particularly in Minnesota, 61 (Reel 3)
    - Correspondence on the Activities of the IWW, 1917-1918; 62 (Reel 3)
    - General Correspondence of the President's Mediation Commission, 1918-1919; 63 (Reel 3)